all right welcome
back here with Alexi tolinski a friend
and colleague and collaborator on this
paper temporal depth in a coherent self
and in depersonalization theoretical
model so go for
[Music]
it well uh I'd like to say hello to
everyone and thank you for being with us
after such a long and fruitful day at uh
6: p.m. on on the east coast and uh it
say I appreciate your interest and thank
you Daniel thank you active inference
Institute for this fantastic Symposium
um so uh uh we'll be working talking
today about this paper on dissociative
States and it's a collective effort uh
this paper is in peer review right now
uh early uh preprint was posted uh on
the site and it was uh a work by Michael
Levan Chris Fields lanot D Costa Rachel
Murphy Daniel who is here uh David
Pinkus and
myself and um this is the link to the
paper if you'd like to take a look at
the earlyer print uh perhaps some of you
would like maybe to get a feel for what
we're talking about and this is not the
patients account this is a a poem uh
from uh Kurt V and his song Pretty
pumpkin I woke up this morning didn't
recognize the man in the mirror then I
laughed and I said oh s me that's just
me then I proceeded to brush some
strangers teeth but they were my teeth
and I was weightless just quivering like
some Leaf come in the window of a
restroom um and this uh poem was cited
by Paul moleno he's a specialist on did
in England on the Psychiatry and
Psychotherapy podcast you can also find
patients account on YouTube I couldn't
post the video here for copyright
reasons um so dissociations are a
spectrum and they range from mild to
severe transient uh to Chronic they can
be benign and pathological and certainly
they're not a bright line category uh
the causes vary for them as well we call
it iology in the clinical World they can
be caused by psychological trauma
neurological conditions substances
seizures anesthesia and uh different
sleep phases there's a subset of
conditions here we call dissociative
disorders typically in the history of
these patients we see prolonged
elevation of stress accompanied by
repeated traumatic experiences in
circumstances where they feel There Is
No Escape typically childhood abuse and
neglect and we call that complex trauma
which has a different presentation than
acute trauma and we'll touch upon why
this specific pathway of iology uh is is
important for dissociative
disorders um
well I'd like to say why uh this matters
what's at stake what's the motivation
for this paper and we have many authors
and they have variable motivations but
I'm a clinician I see patients all day
and um uh for me the main reason for
that is these conditions are hard to
diagnose many patients go undiagnosed
for a long time they're very hard to
treat uh and we're sometimes content
with partial results and the risk of
self harm or suicide is higher for these
patients and there are many many reasons
for that uh we think that perhaps one of
the reasons is that there is no unified
theory of dissociations we have kind of
um neurobiological ideas the corticol
limic inhibition hypothesis we have uh
psychodynamic ideas we have uh attempts
to model dissociations from first
principles by anuna and other colleagues
but uh these different attempts are not
tied together and certainly not tied
together with the patients uh subjective
experiences so we are trying to make
steps in that direction and we don't
claim that we've built a unified theory
of dissociations but what we're doing
here is we're focusing on one aspect of
dissociations one focal point that is a
collapse of the temporal depth in any
kind of dissociation regardless of the
cause by temporal depth we mean how far
into the future the person can plan
what we're hoping for is that this uh uh
focused approach has the potential to uh
allow us to to to um perhaps develop uh
more accurate diagnostic uh uh
procedures and and to possibly um help
increase efficacy in in therapy with
full respect to how difficult complex
and messy this work is um uh additional
point of convergence is we explore
multiple theoretical perspectives in the
paper and they all converge on the same
um points and here is the main thesis um
the collapse of the temporal depth is
necessary and sufficient for the onset
of a dissociative episode so we're going
a little bit further than colleagues who
already mentioned a relationship between
temporal depth and
associations Dean and and Anna yunik and
others and Carl friston were saying it's
causal that there is no dissociation
without the temporal depth collapse and
the collapse of the temporal depth will
reliably lead to dissociative episode
both we are um uh saying that temporal
depth collapse can be conceptualized as
a common pathway for the onset of
dissociative symptoms regardless of
itology and finally we suggest that the
focus on restoring the temporal depth
can be an effective strategy in
therapeutic
interventions one of the theoretical
perspectives we explored in the paper is
Michael 11's te framework technological
approach to mind everywhere which I
think is very useful uh and
unfortunately I haven't seen many
uh attempts to uh use it in clinical
applications this is the title and the
link to the paper uh there's so much in
Michael Len's work that is useful uh his
uh paper on cancer which is based on his
experiments is also one of The
Inspirations for our paper here but
here's another inspiration if you dive
into Mike's work you'll probably see uh
what he claims based on experiments that
all intelligences are collective
intelligences however ever at our
subjective level at the level of the
conscious mind we don't feel that way uh
we perceive unity all our percepts
Sensations thoughts feelings come
together in a cohesive and coherent
whole a single conscious experience in
the here and now and uh we will talk
about this seeming uh Paradox uh if you
wish in in our paper um some of the core
tenants of the team framework not all of
them but some key points uh commitment
to graduality the there is no bright
lines uh Michael suggests that
intelligence is built gradually and uh
by accumulation of complexity material
Independence uh our model is not based
on neurons or central nervous system we
will talk certainly about a subset you
know I'm a clinician I work with human
beings so we'll talk about brain-based
models but generally the model applies
to synthetic agents and cells that are
not neurons commitment to empirical uh
research as opposed to just exchange of
opinions on the subject um Dynamics the
C are not fixed they're malleable and
plastic and cell can be nested and
overlapping cooperating and competing
both laterally and across
levels uh this is an illustration of one
of the key Concepts in Len's framework
um uh called a light con and what you
see here depicted is various organisms
in the middle of the slide you see a
tick and a dog a human being possible AI
by compound intelligence such as an end
colony and you see this sort of nested
and embedded structure on the picture on
the right and L cone has two uh
Dimensions there's a spatial Dimension
and and a on the horizontal plane and
the vertical Dimension is temporal and
TI for example is not particularly
concerned uh with things happening a
mile away uh it cannot recall far from
the past and plan far into the future
well human beings are capable of uh
planning things until uh uh that happen
after we die a living will and uh with
the use of language and culture and
books we can uh use things that happened
before we were born so we're capable of
huge light cones and I'm highlighting
this word capable of it doesn't mean
that in our wakeful hours alert hours we
are walking around with the significant
light cones they contast contract and
expand the depending on various
circumstances but we're certainly
capable of them while ticks or
not and the vertical dimension of a
lyone is exactly what we mentioned
before that is the temporal depth there
is of course a perspective on the same
thing in fap and I like this very Su
phras by Carl friston who said because
consequences follow causes the
generative model acquires a temporal
depth and more formally uh some agents
are only capable of modeling their
immediate environment and in the Here
and Now While others are capable of
planning actions into the future and the
generative models capable of planning
are referred to as temporally deep
generative models so temporal depth
under fep is the length of the temporal
Horizon that is considered during
planning uh we're moving on to
describing the if you wish healthy self
um and we do mention that it is a
materially independent um structure
where you know in principle we can talk
about of the selves of synthetic agents
and you know cell
collectives uh uh selves depend on an
organism's ability to infer and here we
will uh provide uh a viewpoint on the
two clinical terms familiar to
clinicians such as derealization and
depersonalization so the organism's
beliefs about the world are the
inferences about the external
environment and the Continuum of issues
in this process we will call
derealization while the organism's
beliefs about its own internal milu its
body and mind we will call the self and
the Continuum of issues of this process
we will call
depersonalization the S are hierarchical
composite nested and with boundaries uh
so we consider self to be a system
consisting of hierarchically structured
beliefs which effectively makes it a
dynamic hierarchical generative model
and taken in its entirety the self is
informationally separated from the
external environment by a mark of
blanket or near Mark of blanket by
boundary would like to emphasize I
apologize if this is Trivial to the
audience of the active inference
Institute that this boundary is not
Material like skin it is
informational uh through which the self
and not self interact so to emphasize
the self as we have defined it is a
model it is not an organism the organism
constructs and implements it so the self
is quite literally the construction of
the mind this is an illustration of that
from early work by Michael Lan I think
this was his doctoral dissertation
materials and what you see here is um
Duc embos that started from oite and
then you have blastoderm you after cell
division you have a collection of cells
and at the top left if nothing is done
then this blastoderm will develop into a
single ducky you see this green shrimpy
looking thing that's a single
duck however if you introduce a scratch
in this blastoderm and the wound heals
the same exact cell Collective May
develop
into twins or triplets you see the red
yellow and green duckies now think about
that for a moment what happened
here um this Collective of cells
computed what is me and what is not me
and the hardware did not change but in
one case it made a decision that this is
all me and the rest of it is not me and
another one it says there's three mes so
you can see that this is not
Hardware um
s are also as I mentioned hierarchical
composite nested and they have
boundaries so now we're moving on to
components of the self uh that are each
component is separated by their own
boundary and Mark of blanket and because
we're using the word hierarchical uh we
will uh Define that there is a core self
a core component if you'd like a visual
metaphor that Mark SS uses we can think
about an onion and there's different
levels of the layers of the on and
there's a core uh in the
middle we will talk about that as
applied to humans and mammals and
rodents so now we are in organic uh in
organisms uh this term is from effective
Neuroscience from Yak pip and Lucid
Bin's book um and also you know I
believe SS and teral used it uh so core
self is non-reflexive non-reflexive and
dominated by raw
feelings uh and part of purely effective
core form of
Consciousness so the effective
homeostatic mechanisms allow an animal
to problem solve in novel environments
and I'll give you an illustration from
Mark SS um to maybe just um bring it
home uh imagine that I'm in the room
full of carbon monoxide and I've never
been in that
before uh so I don't really know what to
do but I feel badly I feel badly in a
very specific way there's air hunger
Suffocation
distress uh and let's say I'm moving
around the room but if I move to the
left and I feel a little bit better and
that's information and if I move to the
right and I feel worse that's also
information perhaps there's a door on
the left and there's a draft underneath
the door and I feel better so this
Compass this internal mechanism the
homeostatic mechanism allowed me to find
out a possible
solution and um we have a whole
collection of these and to mention you
know the actual hunger uh for food and
thirst and
social homeostats such as rage and fear
and panic separation distress Etc so the
collection of that is what punp and SS
conceptualized as the core self uh uh
therefore the set of predictions in the
core self that all the life sustaining
effects will be at or near their
settling points which means in emotional
terms contentment all my needs are met I
am a okay thank you very much right and
that is the minimum of the variational
fre energy if there are deviations from
it such as hunger or thirst or uh air
hunger then that would be a prediction
error accompanied by a negative feeling
like in the example that I used
above uh in mammals we're not putting
the equal sign but we're describing the
anatomical structures that are uh
participating in in uh serving this
function we're talking about the upper
brain stem regions including the
reticular activating system and the
periductal gray they mediate the
function of the core self and you can
see a lot more details in Mark's book
Hidden Spring a journey to the source of
Consciousness so um or self is thought
to be present in animals without the
cortex such as decorticated cats that
are actually more effective and not less
and the cases of human children born
without a cortex hydrolic children they
have emotions when you know uh you put a
brother on on the girl's you know uh
chest she smile smes and she cries so
the core self does not require a
functional
neocortex the higher levels of the brain
structures in humans including the
vortex mediate the higher levels of both
Consciousness and the self and sometimes
it's referred to as extended
Consciousness which allows us to reflect
on what's going on such as to say I feel
anxious right
now uh there is an a symmetry in this uh
um model where the higher levels the
peripheral levels of of the self and and
Consciousness cannot exist without the
core um while their verse is not true
the core can exist without the higher
levels one of the other illustrations uh
of that which PM cites this is based on
Fisher's work in 2016 is that a tiny
lesion a 2 cubic millimeter lesion in a
parabal nucleus will reliably and IR
irreversibly reduce a coma the patient
will never become conscious ever again
while you will never have anything like
that happen in the cortex you know this
small lesion in the cortex will not
result in catastrophic outcomes like
that and this is one of the reasons why
neurosurgeons don't usually like to
operate around the brain stem this is
too consequential too
risky so everything was said about
Consciousness the core and extended is
applied to self as well that peripheral
self components cannot function without
the operational core self and we will
illustrate that with specific examples
in humans later on and addition to this
onoff where the thing is completely
operational or not we can talk about the
influence and the core self has the
ability to change the regime of
functioning in other more peripheral
self components by inducing phase
transitions in them and the Brain
mechanism for that is generalized
arousal um when the higher levels of
consciousness are present and functional
then we have representations such as
fruit and vegetables and you know in the
core self we have Raw effect such as I
don't know separation distress or hunger
but with the higher levels of
consciousness presence we are capable of
uh uh thinking things like I want an
apple or the aect the drive is in
Freudian language and in SS language is
attached to the
object and similarly we can have these
constructions about the meta object such
as I uh such as I look pale or I am a
pessimist and I here is a mental object
and therefore I is a metacognitive
construct an abstraction and it only
exists at the higher levels of the self
such as autobiographical self it is not
used or even needed in the core self to
reiterate core self as a system has the
capacity to
detect uh the effective prediction
errors and uh attempt to minimize the
variational free energy through action
without any
eye we're moving on to peripheral self
components and we'll describe only a few
uh and the terminology here is different
from what you may read in wonderful book
by Neil Seth being you so the first one
is autobiographical self and that's a
system dynamically representing our
life's history if you for example
remember your 10th birthday and the cake
is on the table and Mom is there and
your friends are there and the sun is
shining and everyone's smiling and it's
Tuesday that's an episode that's an
episodic memory and a collection of them
organized through time is our sort of
life
narrative um there is a bordly self
which is a system dynamically building
inferences about our body and various
representations and interceptive
processing there's a social self which
is a system representing inferences
about how we are seen by others and how
we present ourselves and act in the
social environment each peripheral self
component such as bodily self for
example has its own Mark of blanket and
each component is embedded into the
whole self and also contains
subcomponents creating a nested
architecture that you saw in the T light
cone picture
before about the unity that in humans at
the higher levels of the self such as at
the autobiographical self level uh uh uh
these these levels create an impression
of a unified experience and this is just
the experience of the autobiographical
self not the entire system the
autobiographical self claims to itself
and others to be the entire self while
it is not
so Anil Seth refers to these things as
delusion we have a delusion of being a
unified I don't know alexity right but
you know what we're saying is that it is
that system that is deluded um uh the
autobiographical self subsystem I'm
ambivalent about using the term diluted
I think it it's not the optimal one
because we use it in the clinical world
and I prefer it uh called inference or
belief that we're unified State
differently we can say that a stable
belief that I'm whole in the um I'm
complete in the autobiographical self um
its generative model contributes to us
feeling as a mtic self therefore the
subjectively perceived Unity the
coherence of the self is an
inference related to coherence another
thing we can talk about is continuity
and nearly is a theology stemming from
the definition of Mark of blanket our
self remain the same persistent time
while all the processes or
Communications across its Mark of
blanket remain
functional and we can um offer you
another viewpoint on the same exact
phenomenon from if you wish more
neurobiological perspective or
psychological
perspective if you recall maybe you're
at the train station or you know
anywhere in the city and you see someone
and you think you recognize them but
you're not sure you know this sensation
of recognition of familiar uh so the
familiarity novelty calculations is what
we're talking about here and
depersonalization is a breakdown in that
something that is familiar myself
suddenly abruptly becomes very novel and
not
recognized but actually these
calculations neurobiologically are not
uh bright line dichotomous categories
they are probabilistic and they are
Spectrum but we course grain them in the
mind often into yes or no familiar or
novel so that subjective impression of
yes I know this person or not is just
the course grading of the continuous
variable representational capacity is
important uh the Deep generative model
implies that the agent is capable of
planning into the future which in turn
requires an ability to generate store
and retrieve counterfactual data
generate store and retrieve as
memory so therefore when the
representational capacity is completely
or partially impaired for any reason the
agent completely or partially loses an
ability to infer leading to
depersonalization and der
realization if we talk about health and
pathology briefly the two key terms here
are voluntary and involuntary you know
again all of us during our day we can
either sit down to plan things you know
for you know 10 year temporal Horizon
which expands our temporal uh depth or
when we uh meditate or uh rock climb you
know then we can be more in the moment
in the here and
now but uh trauma doesn't ask per I mean
perpetrators are you know there's
nothing voluntary about it and so that's
an involuntary collapse of the temporal
depth uh which usually is leading to
pathological
conditions this is a perspective from
the nonlinear dynamical systems you know
if again I am in uh you know adult
healthy alert functioning and I may have
small deviations from I IM me say I'm
daydreaming or something like that and
the collection of these points from
which I rely ably return to ime can be
described as the attractor Basin and the
whole thing in terms of attractor
landscape is the set point attractor
regime ime and ime would be the
variational free energy minimum and that
is a fairly stable system perhaps in the
autobiographical sum right now in order
to for that system to change some energy
uh needs to be applied and with external
interference of sufficient power this
attractor landscape can change when that
power is applied temporarily there's a
phase transition the attractor landscape
evolves into something else perhaps
during that transition you have a chotic
regime and if we are in the case of
trauma then the functioning can be
chotic for a while but then it may
settle down so to speak into one of the
possible post-traumatic presentations
there may be multiple postraumatic
presentations and one of the possible
options is depicted here this is not
again Universal but you know it's one of
the possible options what you see here
is a multiple coexisting uh Point
attractors represented by local Minima
of the variation free
energy and they can correspond to Alters
in D
ID uh and in this example you also see
that they're surrounded by a global
minimum variation of free energy now
also if you look at the uh area the
region between the local Minima then in
dynamic IAL systems that's called a
repeller and uh repellers are uh
notoriously chaotic so uh that suggest
that you may not have very good
predictability of how you will
transition from alra X to alra y or alra
z uh to say a few more words about
this when we switch between the altars
then we are in regime of itinerancy this
is the term Carl Frist likes to use a
lot and you know justifiably so also
when we have transitions from X Ultra X
to Y that the time is disrupted you know
in the idea you don't have this flowing
continuity of time there's a series of
disruptions effectively then your uh
coherent large light cone is broken into
uh pieces
here now imagine that this patient with
with this condition reached out for help
and they want to get better but this uh
attractor landscape already acquired
some stability and so again we need some
interference to destabilize the
pathological
regime the difference here would be that
in therapy in the process of healing the
this uh destabilization of the
pathological attractor landscape is
voluntary controlled and guided ideally
by a licensed and competent mental
health professional and uh that's that's
the uh the difference from the onset of
uh acute trauma so Psychotherapy can be
once such intervention and it's the
treatment of choice we have very limited
efficacy with medications and now it's
very uh uh uh kind of um fashionable to
talk about augmentation with psychedelic
treatment or perhaps neuros stimulation
it's important to say that just
destabilizing that landscape doesn't
guarantee anything at all so when people
present this idea that you just go to
like I don't know and have some iasa or
anything ketamine infusion and you're
better is a myth because you know the
important part is that the patient
settles back into health and just the
destabilization of this landscape
doesn't lead to that you still need uh
therapy you still need you know to
process the trauma not just to
destabilize the pathological
regime um and that therapeutic process
when you destabilize the the
pathological attractive landscape is
another phase transition temporarily
temporarily chaotic with the idea that
eventually it leads you to a healthier
functioning either a attractive
landscape corresponding to cohesive uh
system or at least a little more
coherent system with less Alters partial
Improvement let's talk a little bit more
about the phase transition so before
things happen in in in health we have a
nested and embedded uh
self and that can be described in in FB
is a hierarchy of coupled interconnected
attractors car friston you know uh wrote
that slower attractor can possibly
control the phase transition of the
faster
attractor and in our system the core
self is is feeling based it's effective
and it's one of the components uh of uh
effects of feelings is generalized
arousal and we know that the CH changes
in generalized arousal level can lead to
the phase transitions of the entire
neuroc cortex from periodic to chaotic
State and back so this is one of the
possible uh kind of you know uh
explanation in our model how this works
the phase
transitions um you know a few more uh um
thoughts about it trauma is not a um
guided transition it's an effective
storm it's a flood of cortisol that is
abrupt and severe and that uh abrupt
increase in generalized arousal leading
to the destabilization of a healthy
attractor landscape in the
autobiographical self but then when
there's an onset of a dissociative
syndrome after trauma then uh the regime
settles down to a lower energy uh
perhaps effective numbness that patients
talk about and in a a Psychotherapy not
immediately but when the patient is
ready which can take a year or more you
know when there's active trauma work
then there is again an increase in in
energy level with with the idea
eventually to settle down to a healthier
regime of
functioning a few clinical observations
starting from dissociative disorders
which are conceptualized traditionally
as uh defensive response to prolonged
and inescapable
trauma clinicians talk about uh and
patients report this this quality of
emotional flatness or deadness or
numbing sometimes they call it
freeze so in our model it corresponds to
issues with Communications between the
core self and the peripheral self
components for example that
autobiographical self in this regime
operates as if it is uninformed by the
vital emotional informational flows that
reaching in the core self one of the
possible ways it can be achieved not the
only way but one of them is the frontal
prefrontal cortex inhibiting the lyic
structures that's the cortical lyic
inhibition hypothesis and in fep terms
that means lowering of precision
associated with effective prediction
error
messages um we're moving on to also
severe dissociations but temporary such
as general anesthesia propol and uh uh
uh it's a very found change in the body
that influences the Gap Junctions
between the
cells and recovery from anesthesia is a
very interesting process Michael Lan is
fascinated with it it's actually a
little bit of a miracle that we come
back to be the same person we have been
before and some people don't uh you may
wake up a pirate uh and uh these
conditions are called post-operative
delirium dissociative Amnesia
post-operative cognitive dysfunction
this is also an illustration itself is
computed and plastic and malleable it's
not hard um you know Hardware um and
perhaps we get oriented with the use of
our memory systems including the
episodic memories another severe case is
a seizure where not only
autobiographical self is impaired but
also the social and the bodily self and
one of the reasons for that is the
necessary resources for the functioning
of the self components are not
operational in
seizure uh moderate dissociations uh in
neurological cases but permanent ones
are for example the perhaps one of the
most famous neurological patients hm who
had a bilateral hpoc compus damage uh
and uh in Britain there's Clyde wearing
and Anil Seth describes Clyde wearing in
his book being you this patients do not
have episodic memory encoding and
effectively they live in about 10
minutes of the here and now uh there is
no past and no future beyond that and if
you read Clyde wearing's diaries that he
talks about the ser of Awakenings he
said oh I just woke up and 10 minutes
later oh I woke up and then I woke up
and if you show these Diaries to a
clinician who is an expert in did they
will which I've done you know I talked
to Roxy wolf one of the fellows of the
international Society for the study of
Trum associations and she said that you
know this patient looks perpetually
depersonalized there is no continuity
itself Corso patients they don't recall
the past they can fabulate the past and
in Alzheimer's in early phases there's
issue with recent autobiographical
memories but some access to the remote
autobiographical memories all of these
cases are discontinuity in
autobiographical
self um uh more frequent perhaps cases
or substances ketamin I doses of THC or
iasa lead to depersonalization and
dualization and importantly if you read
the studies then these patients actually
report they tell you that their sense of
time is impaired not only that the
planning is impaired as well um if you
have a alcohol blockout and the person
tells you on Wednesday that they have no
idea whatsoever what happened on Tuesday
after 6 then uh this is a discontinuity
this is a gap in episodic
memory uh there's also something called
traumatic Amnesia there very said cases
of high school shootings where you know
the person literally doesn't remember
you know 15 minutes of what was
happening in the
cafeteria what happens in acute PTSD is
that you know uh hippocampus is reaching
cortisol receptors and there's a flood
of cortisol and the effectively the
episodic memory of trauma the cohesive
context contextual time stamp memory is
not laid down in a stable fashion you
have shards of glass you have phobic
memories semantic memories procedural
memories but not the episodic one which
is also discontinuity autobiographical
self and that is
involuntary uh and we talked about mild
benign everyday uh dissociations uh next
time you wake up you know maybe tomorrow
the day after you know try to monitor
how what's going on uh and you may catch
that pH of what met singer calls you
know a non-ic self where things are just
flowing through your mind but your eye
is not fully out borous
yet uh to summarize the level of
consciousness regime of Consciousness
pathological States and all the
underlying resources necessary for the
successful operation of each self
component collectively influence the
complex dynamics of the
system um a neurobiological perspective
briefly the historically most famous one
is uh cortical limic inhibition
hypothesis by Sierra and barus who
postulated that uh prefrontal cortex is
uh inhibiting the lyic structures
including the amydala and the interior
singular cortex
ACC the subsequent studies don't fully
support that hypothesis but partially
support it I like the work by Ruth
lenius and her colleagues and guess what
you know her uh revision her refinement
of the cortical liic inhibition adds
Dynamics transience context and
itinerancy all the things we
like uh uh uh they talk about two
regimes even in patients with
dissociative syndromes over modulation
and under modulation ation again
itinerancy in not one regime but
multiple regimes over modulation is
indeed hypoactive amigdala and
hyperactive prefrontal cortex which is
described above but also these patients
less frequently but but you can see it
in a reverse regime where amydala is
active and and PFC is less
active uh uh over modulation dominates
in dissociative uh conditions they
refined the anatomical Network and
talked about different sub regions of
amydala the central medial amydala
basolateral amydala dorsolateral
periductal gray vental lateral
periductal gray Thalamus and other
regions and this network of regions
collectively Works to create specific
post tromatic regimes they also
described uh the regime where patient
has access to painful memories usually
uh is accompanied by under modulation
very active state with amigdala active
and uh when they don't have access to
painful memories they're more in a
dissociative State we can also briefly
talk about what are the anatomical
substrates and the neuros psychological
substrates of the temporal depth
collapse and again acute trauma hpoc
compal damage and dementia are affect
the episodic memory
system uh if there's an insulin damage
then you can expect the disruption in
the bodily memories and perhaps in
camine use you may have a dysfunction of
prefrontal Cortex and frontoparietal
Network
which renders the work in memory uh of
the patient dysfunctional you can
imagine other circumstances when you
have PFC in front of paral network
impaired that usually leads to a
psychotic state where you know it's very
hard to think you know we need work in
memory to be able to
think um about dissociative disorders
again the point made at the very
beginning that prolonged inescapable
exposure to highly stressful
environments can be seen as lasting
stress beyond the agent's ability to
manage which results in the breakdown of
um tame light into the uh components a
fragmentation decoherence and
discontinuity when the landscape uh
attractor and repell Landscape
corresponding to a pathological
condition takes root and in contrast to
that if you look at the single uh
episode of camine intoxication then you
have transient working memory disruption
leading to transient
dissociation again to summarize lasting
or temporary severe or mild dissociative
experiences are accompanied by the
collapse of the self temporal depth and
we are ready for discussion which I very
much look forward
to thank you Lexi great
presentation thank
you
okay where should we begin what would be
interesting or or given where the work
has gotten over the last few
weeks where what do you feel like is
most
relevant well perhaps any colleagues
have comments I don't know if Jus is
with us and he's a esteemed neuros
psychiatrist and he sees a lot of
patients and perhaps neurological
patients and he can comment on some of
the things we've mentioned I I had a uh
clinical meeting with with uh colleagues
who do a lot of dissociative works and I
mean I'm seeking feedback and critique
and so whatever ever people have
whatever thoughts people have yeah if
there's anyone in live chat they can
write a question a few pieces that stuck
out differently in how you presented it
uh in comparison from working on the
paper was the narrative self's role in
the
maintenance of
The Narrative of
unity and about what is the experiencer
of that
or is that all it can do why does it do
that why does the autobiographical self
have that kind of a voice or a cognitive
function is audio working okay can yeah
can we hear each other I I think why is
a tricky question you know it might also
be tell logical question I would say
that it's probably functional you know
uh for us to have coherence elves uh and
um I don't know why uh but
um we are observing it so we have
descriptive level we have observations
that I feel like the same Elixir and
it's a little bit of a miracle that as
we know that the cells in the organisms
they are they die and they're born but I
still feel like the the same person
even so uh we change developmentally I'm
not the same person as I have been at
age 5 or age 15 but I still maintain
this story if you wish this believe that
I am the same and um I also protect the
internal milu from external threats you
know of the same organism and if we look
at other species say an oak tree that
you know uh grows from an acorn it is
still the same Oak it's the same organ
uh so um I I perhaps in biology as well
there's a need uh for the system inside
the mark of blanket to maintain that
saying whatever is inside the mark of
blanket is the same
me but it is a belief you know and uh
um I don't know if I'm answering your
question maybe I'm just free associating
to it so yeah is that a clinically valid
method um well it it reminds me of
mortal computing and there's a lot of
focus on how behavioral activities in a
niche relate to the material stability
and I think you really Drew carefully on
Mike Levan at all's work to talk about
the analgous
Dynamics on a landscape of a
narrative self and that's just kind of
that was like a trampoline but then you
also complicated that with multiple
elves like the social and the narrative
and so then there are these
multiple
disassociative or like it's kind of they
each have their
own
unity and yet they can be discordant and
unified and so then is there any general
framework for different possibilities
open-endedly of different regimes
these are great questions or even maybe
challenges to develop it further but I
agree with you if we look in the bodily
self right I don't perceive my hand to
be a separate entity I believe I I feel
for it to be part of the whole organism
myself my body right and so in the
bodily self there's also a level of
unity I'm just saying that this is again
a computation within that specific sub
system that my body is one whole self
and we can see how that gets uh perhaps
distorted in somatoparaphrenia or even
rubber hand illusion where uh this hand
is perceived as not you know so uh and
so we see that the system is plastic and
malleable and and prone to change but
and when when no uh interference is
happening it continues to be cohesive is
one body and one mind you know this
autobiographical I I I've noticed you Ed
the term narrative uh self I think that
Anil Seth's term and I prefer
autobiographical for the reason that uh
rats they have episodic memories and
they don't have our verbal
abilities um uh and so they they also
have episodic memories which are what we
when the contextual memories right and I
think that uh there's the same eye in
all autobiographical memories and that's
the
unity uh
yeah yeah thanks you a few it's it's it
it it probably is more accurate to say
it's a narrative cognitive capacity that
encompasses autobiographical or Alo
biographical type narratives um and I'm
reminded of uh NPR radio discussion from
a few days ago that I listened about
Memoir and about what Memoir was and
could it only be written when the person
did or didn't change a lot but what or
who doesn't change
in every single one of these ways so
then what would that mean like what so
that that that was kind of a funny
connection and then and then um do you
have any thoughts on that or have
another active comment no I'm just
enjoying your comment I don't know if I
have a a I thought on that yeah you
you've see many clinical Memoirs and
presentations of self- understandings
and all of this so there's just so
many and it gets
brought
out so
sparsely like and
indirectly and it makes a lot of sense
to the person who might be saying it but
that that could you could be too or not
confident enough about
that interesting you brought it up thank
you for that Daniel I think that you
know when we theorize say in Dynamic
theories then we uh usually think about
different sub agencies of the mind like
Freud for example in his know structural
model he had the Eid ego and super ego
where I want pistachio Asam is the Eid
and pistachio es is fat and calories
that's the super ego response and stash
esum is $4 and you have three and a half
is the ego uh but there's a whole bunch
of them we can name a sort of a sub
agency of an internal judge you know
which is sort of super English or a
neutral Observer or uh an accountant
who's running Itali or
and all of this so we all have sort of a
jury there of different kind of regimes
of operation if you wish but uh the
patient is often surprised because when
they for example self- criticize and you
talk about that in therapy and say do
you notice the voice of your judge it's
kind of you know uh not very fair I mean
there's no misdemeanor everything's a
felony and judge is present all the time
like no it's not it's me I'm doing it
you know I screwed up you know so again
you know they default regime is is me
myself and I that I am you know I am bad
and when we we discuss these things and
we open it up and we show the different
kind of uh we show a theater with
different voices or a jury with
different representations it's usually
kind of an Insight it's a
surprise but that allows a bit more
control um for the patient in clinical
work soon okay I'll read a question in
the live chat Pablo FM wrote thank you
very much I find it super interesting I
wonder why humans seek for drug
experiences having been so decisive in
human history coffee could be a great
example tea tobacco alcohol have also
been very popular among
civilizations it's a great question I
don't know if I have a good answer it's
a huge question and there's a good paper
you can find it on Google's caller a
pbet by me zelner Mark SS and other
colleagues I think Yak pip was alive
it's called why depression feels bad and
what do addicts really want and it's
based on effective neuroscience and what
it postulates is that uh of course there
are individuals who have multiple drugs
that they are you know using all the
time so there's an upper and the downer
and other things but there are usually
some innate kind of predispositions
where people who are wound up in tense
they sometimes crave alcohol because
it's uh binding to the Gaba receptors
and it's sort of you know sedating us a
little bit it makes you a little more
less kind of wired up people who are
very painfully lonely and uh uh detached
and they crave human uh comfort and you
know to feel together and loved and
accepted they may if they discover
opioids that would be a you know lock
and key match that would be a dangerous
combination um and uh perhaps when
somebody's oriented to Performance and
they're very bored all the time and they
want to something you know to do better
and more they may gravitate toward uh
stimulants and so there's these things
uh and there's some common factors among
different agents uh such as you know I
believe that multiple substances they
have the dopaminergic effect and you
know a lot of motivations are subjective
in individuals I've had patients say
that I'm smoking pot to slow down
time I've had patients tell me that you
know p is my oldest friend I've been
doing it long longer than any person
that I've been with uh some people seek
this state of numbness and they want to
kind of not feel as acutely they want to
sort of feel desensitized so these
states of dissociation can be desired um
and that's briefly I guess what I what I
wanted to say about it so well thank
you I'm reminded of a comment from ma in
the live chat earlier this morning
and she was kind of pointing to
how one mode of how we've seen active
inference applied in these presentations
is looking like athology at the
sequences of behavior but not really
looking at the self-maintenance as a
behavior like especially talking about
digital
agents or or that it's just about what
do they perceive what do they do it's
taken as a granted or a separate
question how they
exist yet also there's this
self-maintenance
self-reconstruction
character that doesn't even need to have
anything to do with the athology its
Dynamics can just be like
morphologically playing
out not necessarily doing some cognitive
task out in the world in any
particularly effective
way yeah it's a very interesting thought
and for some reason I'll allow myself
the Liberty to free associate again it
reminded me of yal Harari who went
interviewed he said you guys go to the
gym You observe your diet and you take
care of your body and he said I take
care of my mind I meditate an hour a day
and uh it goes to silent Retreat a month
and a year and the interviewer
challenged him I think he was from The
Daily Show he said how do you manage
that and her said I got no kids you know
so but in addition to that he's also in
therapy so there's a uh that idea of
really maintaining the mind and not just
the body with behaviors we're all
oriented to what do I do do do what do I
think think think which are sort of
verbal virtual behaviors but how do you
feel as my great colleague Raji uh
Warrior says we're human beings not
human doings we have a very tough time
being we're all about doing more that's
true and so uh yeah and also Harari
talks about informational hygiene where
a lot of stuff in the social media is
noise and trash and a lot of it is
consumed and we have pollution but you
know so he doesn't do you know he reads
books and he thinks in Millennia but I
don't know I mean I went sideways from
your comment but it's just that's what
where my thought went so yeah
it it seemed like a very relevance when
people are discussing the the the unity
or the articulation of Mind and Body
which is kind of what this unified
promise on the cover of the textbook
suggests is what what would it be to
have a unified model of brain mind
behavior and so
on then the the analogy or the
connection with the physical and the
cognitive is
just it has to be taken as a starting
point not like a hot
take yeah
yeah but what you just said reminded me
when I read Michael Len's work and got
more familiar with it I actually had
regret I'm like why were we not taught
that that was a bit of a revolution in
my mind it was a big pivot because if
you go through graduate program in
psychology it's all about the unity you
know I am the same you know cohesive and
coherent and the fact that we have
intelligence at the level of individual
cells and then the cell Collective and
then tissue and organ and all of this
thing that I think is one montic Alexi
is a pyramid with Communications bottom
up and top down and laterally is is a
revolution I think that you know I I
wonder what models of psychology can be
built with that and they don't exist yet
it's all about one big block and what
happens to it I am depressed you know
there's no collectives this is one big
block
right yeah it's a really important
Insight I think that's the kind
of frictions and and experiences will
start to learn more about and see
produce in different ways like just
seeing how you connected the topics to
specific quotes translated the ontology
re reworded
descriptions using kind of like a
translation sometimes really just as
simple as a lookup of words just authors
using one word and being able to see an
otim onology
term equivalent or roughly
related it's uh and
and what what does that look like or I
guess as your last comments what do you
think after to the paper after this now
like what are the
directions towards which people would
say okay that's applying active
inference in a clinical
setting I my goal eventually I think is
to get to Therapeutics and for example
you know um actually I probably will not
use that example it's it's a good
material for the second paper that we'll
follow up with uh but I I do think that
you know the question is what do we do
in therapy differently how do we
understand how do we formulate cases
differently with this information I I
haven't heard it clearly said out loud
in the did literature there's a lot of
perspectives there's a lot of endless
complexity and there's a lot of nuance
but if we can highlight a central point
and say there is a temporal depth
collapse I think it allows us to do
something with it in clinical work and
in diagnostic work and that's my hope it
may not materialize but this is what I'm
hoping for so
well even from a
researcher's
ethological perspective it's kind of
like that's the transferable and the
interesting research question how could
you be
observing not on the inside and make
some kind of inference or assessment
that would matter clinically with no map
territory pretense not that it's 100%
reliability just taking a clear look at
the
Diagnostics available rethinking it from
dynamical systems
perspective maybe different uh
Biometrics maybe pupil it's like it's
not it's just kind of that's the open
question and then where it provides
clinical utility
that's where it
matters yeah thank you perfectly said
yeah I agree okay thank you
Alexi see you thank you Daniel see you
byebye e